In the first lesson,
最初の講義では
you saw some best planning algorithms,
モーションプランニング問題を解決する
which solve the motion planning problem.
最適なプランニングアルゴリズムをご覧いただきますが
But we never formally defined that problem. I'd like to do that now.
私たちは問題をまだ定義していませんでしたここでやってみたいと思います
Now, there is a word that you might encounter quite a bit
モーションプランニングアルゴリズムに関する資料を読み始めると
if you start reading material regarding motion planning algorithm.
よく目にするワードがあります
That word is "configuration space," which defines
「コンフィギュレーションスペース」と言われるもので
all the possible configurations of a robot in the given world.
与えられた世界のロボットの設定をすべて定義します
Consider the maze word you saw in the first lesson where these words were all 2D grids,
最初の講義でお見せした２次元グリッドの迷路命令を考えてみましょう
the robot configuration was sometimes two
座標 x と y で表すときロボットコンフィギュレーションは 2 次元であり
dimensional when we presented it as an x_y point,
ロボットの方向を追加した場合には
and sometimes three dimensional when also including the robot's heading.
3 次元となります
In fact, the configuration space for vehicle that can become
実際 車両用のコンフィギュレーションスペースは
even larger depending on what motion planning algorithms we decide to use.
使用するモーションプランニングアルゴリズによってむしろ広げることが可能です
With this idea of configuration space in mind,
このコンフィギュレーションスペースの考え方を覚えておくと
we can define a motion planning problem as follows.
以下に述べる 3 つの事項で
We're given three things.
モーションプランニングを定義できます
An initial configuration, a goal configuration
初期コンフィギュレーション ゴールコンフィギュレーション
and also some constraints describing how the vehicle was allowed to move,
またどのように車両を動かすか そのダイナミックス
its dynamics and the description of the environment.
そして環境の説明などを記述する制約です
Here, it is important to understand how this connects to
最近学習した他の意思決定モデルとどのようにつなぐのか
the other decision-making modules that you have recently learned about.
理解することが重要です
Usually, the start configuration is the current configuration of the car given to us by
通常 スタートコンフィギュレーションは 車の位置
the localization value and the sensors that give us information about car location,
速度 進む際の加速などの情報を提供する
speed, acceleration they can go, etcetera.
ローカライゼーションやセンサーから得られる値のカレントコンフィギュレーションのことです
The behavior layer gives us a desired end configuration,
挙動レイヤーは目的のエンドコンフィギュレーションと
and maybe some constraints regarding where to go and at which speed.
行き先や速度に関する制約などを提供します
Finally, the prediction completes this problem by giving us
最後に その後出現する障害物領域に関する情報が与えられることで
information about how the obstacle region will evolve in time.
予測はこの問題を終了します
This way, the sequence of actions that we generate takes
このようにして作成した action シーケンスは
into account other vehicles and pedestrian actions.
他の車両や歩行者の動作を考慮しています
And if we're working with a more sophisticated prediction module,
より高度な予測モデルを処理する場合
how our actions might influence them.
action はモデルにどのような影響を与えるでしょうか
The motion planning problem can then be
モーションプランニング問題はコンフィギュレーション空間内の
defined as final sequence of feasible movements in
実行可能な動作の最終シーケンスとして定義されます
the configuration space that's moved the robot from
これによりスタートコンフィギュレーションからエンドコンフィギュレーションまで障害物に当たらずに
a start configuration to an end configuration without hitting any obstacles.
ロボットを動かします
Now, I'm going to ask you to think about configuration spaces in the following questions.
以下の問題では コンフィギュレーション空間について考えていただきます